Let's take a look at what it will
take to implement a very basic SyncAdapter. We're going
to write two services. Each service serves the primary
purpose of delivering an object that represents an Android
Binder interface to one of the system frameworks.
A Binder is actually the low-level glue that implements
cross process communication in Android. You've been using Binders
every time you talk to an Android system service.
Intents and content providers are just high-level abstractions on
top of the Binder interface. There's a whole language known
as AIDL to help define these interfaces. We're not
going to cover all this here, but there's a lot
more you can do with services and Binders. One
more thing before we start, we're going to define an
Authenticator Service and an Authenticator. But it will only
be used by the Android accounts framework to allow us
to create an account. SyncAdaptor's need an account.
And the account framework requires that there be
an authenticator delivered by an authenticator Service. You'll
see that our authenticator is just a series
of stubs, with exceptions that get thrown for
each call just to prove that it isn't
really used. One final note. This section approximately
follows the online training at developer.android.com around sync adapters.
Feel free to look there if you have
any more questions. We're going to create a new
package, sync, to house all of this goodness.
And a new class file for our authenticator. This
code that we're about to paste in really
just comes from the developer.android.com website, and as I
mentioned earlier it's just a stub. You can tell
because we throw exceptions for calling any of the
functions except for the constructor. And one
more file. Create SunshineAuthenticatorService. This is more code
that is written for us. It allows
the account manager to access the empty authenticator
that we just pasted in. Now we add the account type in our strings.xml. The
account type string suggests that it is specific
to our app. If we had many applications
using the same account, we might want
to create just an example.com account. We'll also
begin to clean things up and add
a content authority string. Note that this matches
our content provider string. We'll fix the XML file later so they both use
this same string. We create a new XML resource file, filename
authenticator.xml, with root element account-authenticator.
And you probably noticed that SunshineAuthenticatorService is
actually a service that needs to be registered
with a package manager in AndroidManifest.xml. Here's
some more pasty goodness that does just that.
Now be very, very careful. These strings
all have to match precisely. The error messages
that the system gives for having incorrect accounts
are not necessarily intuitive. And with that you
should be able to create valid accounts. Once again,
this is all just so that the SyncAdapter can be
tied to an account. You don't actually use this
at all. All right, let's tweak our provider tag in
the manifest. We're going to add the syncable attribute.
This just lets Android know that we're planning to synchronize
the content provider with the server. Also, we'll set
android:exported equals false. We had it at the default setting.
Which means that other apps could see our content. Finally,
let's change the authority to use our new string. Now
for some additional permissions. We need to be able to
read and write sync settings. That makes sense. We also
have to authenticate accounts, even though we're not really using
them for anything. None of these permissions are ones users
should be concerned about. But as developers, we always want
to be careful when we have to add new permissions.
Let's create the SunshineSyncAdapter file itself inside
of sync, which extends the abstract threaded sync
adapter class. Hit Ctrl+I and then Ctrl+O
to implement the necessary abstract methods in constructor.
We'll use the first constructor. We'll fill
this out later. As you may recall, the
sync adaptor pattern requires yet another service. So
we're going to create another Java class called SunshineSyncService.
This class is used to deliver the sync adapter Binder to the sync manager.
The Binder is implemented for us by
the abstract threaded sync adapter class. And returned
in the getSyncAdapterBinder method. And now, we
need one more XML file. Create syncadapter.xml with
root element sync-adapter. Once again, this XML
file defines the settings associated with our sync-adapter.
Including it's content authority. The account type that it
syncs. Whether or not it's user visible. Whether it
supports uploading, which changes the way the content provider
interacts with the sync adapter. Allowing parallel syncs and is
always syncable. These settings make sense for this particular
application, and I bet you know what comes next. You're
right. You have to register the sync adapter service
with the package manager. And therefore we have to create
more manifest entries, containing some important metadata. Most
importantly, links to the file we just created. All
right, now we're getting close. Let's start working
on the sync adapter, itself. We'll start with a
helper function to get the dummy sync account
and make sure that it has been created. Then,
we'll add another helper function to our sync adaptor,
to make it easier to test our sync adaptor.